Good morning. Okay,
so today's דף daf is נ"א. Nun Aleph. We pick up at
the bottom of נ' עמוד ב', Nun Amud Bet, very very bottom.
We're discussing the issue that there was a debate about whether you
could play the musical instruments, the חליל chalil specifically, the flute,
on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Debate between רבי יוסי,
Rebbe Yose, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and the חכמים. Chachamim. And the
first position of רבי יוסי Rebbe Yose was that they're debating the
one that was played with the קרבן, korban, and it could be
played you know on any שבת, Shabbos, the music that goes with
the normal קרבנות. korbanot. And the debate was how much is that
the עיקר עבודה ikar avodah of לויים Levi'im and central to the
עבודה avodah of the קרבן, korban, or how much is it the
singing of the לויים Levi'im and that's the debate. When it comes
to the musical instruments that are played on
סוכות, Succos, the night before the שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeiva
etcetera, everybody agrees that that's just שמחה simcha and that cannot be
done on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Again the phrase
of דוחה את השבת docheh es haShabbos is interesting because we're all
dealing with rabbinic issues here and why this is perceived of as
such a problem is a little unclear, but be that as it
may. So the גמרא Gemara wants to say that so that's רבי
יוסי's Rebbe Yose's approach that this is really a debate of what's
central. Is
it the vocal singing or is it the music that normally comes
with the pouring of the libations of a קרבן? korban? And the
גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Papa says
רב פפא, Rav Papa, last three words on נ' עמוד ב', Nun
Amud Bet, top of נ"א עמוד א' Nun Aleph Amud Aleph now,
כתנאי, k'tannai, this question if עיקר שירה בפה ikar shirah b'peh or
עיקר שירה בכלי, ikar shirah b'kli, if the basic שירה shirah that's
supposed to come from the לויים Levi'im and accompany the קרבן korban
is the singing or is it the music, this is a debate
of תנאים. Tannaim. דתנן, D'tnan, as we taught in a משנה, Mishnah,
עבדי כהנים היו. avdei Kohanim hayu. Who were the people that played
the music? Not did the singing, but played the music. So they
were slaves of כהנים, Kohanim, דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rebbe Meir, that's
what רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir says. רבי יוסי אומר, Rebbe Yose omer,
משפחת בית הפגרים mishpachat Beis Ha'pagram ומשפחת בית צפורייא, u'mishpachat Beis Tzipparya,
these are two names of two families,
ומאמאום היו, u'me'Ammaum hayu, and they were from a place called אמאום,
Ammaum, שהיו משיאין לכהונה. shehayu mishi'in lakehunah. They were not themselves כהנים,
Kohanim, they were ישראלים, Yisraelim, but they were from good ייחוס yichus
and
as רש"י Rashi says, their widowed wives would marry you know would
be married amongst the כהנים, Kohanim, the כהנים Kohanim would be particularly
interested in women from these families because they were although they were
ישראלים Yisraelim and not כהנים, Kohanim, they were of good ייחוס. yichus.
So basically he says they were of משפחות מיוחסות mishpachot meyuchasot of
ישראל. Yisrael. That's his position. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר לויים היו.
Rebbe Chanina ben Antigonus omer Levi'im hayu. No, the לויים Levi'im were
the ones who played the music instrument. Whenever we imagine playing of
the musical instruments in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I think we
always imagine the לויים, Levi'im, but it's quite fascinating it's only one
of three opinions here. מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, Mai lav b'hai k'mifligi,
is it not that this is their debate? דמאן דאמר D'man d'amar
עבדים היו, avadim hayu, the one that says that they were slaves,
כסבר kasvar עיקר שירה בפה ikar shirah b'peh holds that it was
really and they couldn't be that the basic עבודה avodah of the
לויים Levi'im you know accompanied the קרבן korban was the music because
then how would you let slaves do it? So it must have
been that it really was the singing that was the עיקר עבודה
ikar avodah and therefore when it came to the music that you
could have the slaves do it, the slaves of the כהנים. Kohanim.
ומאן דאמר לויים היו u-man de-amar Levi'im hayu, and the one that
says no they were לויים, Levi'im, כסבר kasvar עיקר שירה בכלי, ikar
shirah b'kli, that no the basic עבודה avodah of the לויים Levi'im
was the music and therefore it had to be לויים. Levi'im. So
basically meaning what the גמרא Gemara is trying to do is fascinating
is that the גמרא Gemara is saying you know they're not maybe
they're not really debating the facts, maybe they're sort of like debating
like what it could have been or what it should have been
based on based on their understanding of what was
necessary about what was the real עבודה. avodah. So if you think
the real עבודה avodah was the music, so then they say no
it had to be the לויים. Levi'im. If you think the real
עבודה avodah was the singing then they say no probably could have
been someone else. Of course it's a little funny because it's way
too specific to be talking about a legal point, it really feels
like they're talking about a debating historical facts. And let's see and
that's what anyway the גמרא Gemara is going to respond. The גמרא
Gemara says תסברא, tisbra, does that really make sense that they're having
a legal debate here? If that's true and the question and so
רבי יוסי מאי קסבר, Rebbe Yose mai kasvar, when רבי יוסי Rebbe
Yose says no it was מיוחס meyuchas families of ישראל, Yisrael, what's
his position? אי קסבר Ei kasvar עיקר שירה בפה, ikar shirah b'peh,
if he holds the basic עבודה avodah the basic thing that לויים
Levi'im did was singing, so then אפילו עבדים נמי afillu avadim nami
then he shouldn't in principle say it would be okay to have
עבדים. avadim. If they're not debating facts, if they're debating what would
be acceptable he should have no reason to object to the עבדים.
avadim. אי קסבר Ei kasvar עיקר שירה בכלי, ikar shirah b'kli, and
if he said it was basically the music so לויים, Levi'im, so
it would have to be in ישראלים Yisraelim no, it would have
to be לויים Levi'im and not ישראלים. Yisraelim. So they're obviously not
debating what it could be they're debating because A it's too specific
to be talking about a legal point, it really feels like they're
talking about a- it doesn't explain the position that was the middle
position. So obviously they're debating what it was, not what it could
be. אלא, Ela, says the גמרא, Gemara, rather, but, of course, realize
that if they're debating what it was, even if that's true, the
two positions that hold that it was not the לויים Levi'im must,
even if that's what they're, even if they're just talking about facts,
what emerges from the facts that it was not לויים Levi'im is
that עיקר שירה בפה, Ikar shira be-peh, is that that's the Levite
service was not the music. Okay, but so it starts with the
issue of the facts. And therefore the גמרא Gemara says we must
assume, אלא, Ela, דכולי עלמא עיקר שירה בפה. de-kulei alma ikar shira
be-peh. We must assume that everybody agrees that the עיקר Ikar service
of the לויים Levi'im was the singing, because that then allows for
this debate of fact, right, allows for this reality that some people
will claim that the facts are they were slaves, or the facts
that were they were ישראלים. Yisraelim. That fact could only be possible
assuming that what the לויים Levi'im primarily did was the singing. So
therefore everybody has to agree that primarily what the לויים Levi'im did,
their basic עבודה, Avodah, the basic עבודה Avodah of the קרבן Korban
was the singing. And therefore there could be a debate what was
the reality in terms of who did the playing of the musical
instruments. So,
ובהא קמיפלגי, u-ve-ha kamiflegi, this is the debate: דמר סבר הכי הוה
מעשה ומר סבר הכי הוה מעשה. de-mar savar hachi havei ma'aseh u-mar
savar hachi havei ma'aseh. You gotta love it. They're debating the facts,
they're not even debating any הלכה. halakha. Everybody agrees in theory it
could have been anyone. Okay, but למעשה le-ma'aseh was it? Right? So
the music was not the sole, you know, the sole purview of
the לויים. Levi'im. The music could have been anyone. And למעשה le-ma'aseh
who was it? Right? So some say it was this way, some
say it was that way. So they're debating the facts, which is
a possibility of that range of facts if we assume that עיקר
שירה Ikar shira was בפה. be-peh. You got a question, Dov?
What time was it? Yeah, how many generations? Yes, that's a good
question. How does no one's
grandfather? Right. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was a תלמיד talmid of רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, so, you know, it was a good hundred, no
more like, you know, at least let's say a hundred years after.
Okay? How many real facts do we have a hundred by oral
history, you know, from a hundred years ago, right? My grandfather told
me about World War I. Right, but they didn't tell me much.
Right, and I'm sure that somebody else's grandfather could have told them
something else and some of those facts might conflict with one another.
Right.
So... that's amazing how quickly things are lost. Yeah, maybe.
I... yeah, exactly. All this discussion about the עבודה, Avodah, right. It's
a problem. All right, so anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara says...
So they're debating facts. Okay, but now the גמרא Gemara is like,
you know, that's not so interesting, just who cares then? It's just
facts, you know. So then it's really like, you know, these weren't
historians, okay. So why do we care about facts? So I mean
we care about them in terms of their significance, in terms of
הלכה, halakha, in terms of memory, in terms of religious meaning, but
not סתם. stam. So the גמרא Gemara is going to do something
with it. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: למאי נפקא מינה? le-mai nafka mina?
So what difference does it make? Okay, wonderful. This way, that way,
who cares? So the גמרא Gemara says, למעלין מדוכן ליוחסין ולמעשר קמיפלגי.
le-ma'alin mi-duchan le-yuchasin u-le-ma'aser kamiflegi.
So it says קמיפלגי, kamiflegi, but it means what it means is
their debate would be or what would emerge from it, this is
the way תוספות Tosafot reads it, what would emerge from it would
be a נפקא מינה, nafka mina, an implication of whether the fact
that somebody has been on the דוכן. duchan. The דוכן duchan was
the platform, which would, I mean, we call the דוכן duchan where
the כהנים Kohanim do the ברכת כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, but the דוכן
duchan was the platform where the לויים Levi'im sang and where they
played the musical instruments. Okay? So can you assume that if you
saw somebody on the דוכן, duchan, excuse me, not singing but playing
the musical instruments, you saw somebody on the דוכן duchan playing the
musical instrument, can you now assume, oh, I can marry into that
guy's family, or oh, I can give that guy and his family
מעשר? ma'aser? What assumptions can you make about somebody you saw playing
the musical instruments on the
דוכן? duchan? Okay, למעלין מדוכן ליוחסין ולמעשר. le-ma'alin mi-duchan le-yuchasin u-le-ma'aser. יוחסין
yuchasin is in terms of marrying in and מעשר ma'aser is giving
מעשר, ma'aser, assuming he's a לוי Levi קמיפלגי. kamiflegi. מאן דאמר עבדים
היו, man de-amar avadim hayu, the one that says the facts happened
to be, I'm sorry to tell you, the facts were they were
slaves, so קסבר אין מעלין מדוכן ליוחסין ולא למעשר. kasavar ein ma'alin
mi-duchan le-yuchasin ve-lo le-ma'aser. That if you saw somebody doing the playing
the musical instrument, you couldn't marry into that family and you couldn't
give him מעשר. ma'aser. You couldn't assume that just because he was,
"Oh, he played the musical instruments in המקדש," Ha-Mikdash, no, they were
slaves. You got to know that. ומאן דאמר ישראלים היו, u-man de-amar
Yisraelim hayu, the one that says it was, you know, good יחוס
yichus families amongst of ישראל, Yisrael, not
לויים, Levi'im, קסבר מעלין מדוכן ליוחסין. kasavar ma'alin mi-duchan le-yuchasin. If you
saw the somebody play a musical instrument, then you can marry into
his family, he's not a slave, and he's good יחוס, yichus, אבל
לא למעשר. aval lo le-ma'aser. He's not a לוי, Levi, or not
necessarily a לוי, Levi, and therefore you cannot give him מעשר. ma'aser.
ומאן דאמר U'man d'amar לויים היו, Levi'im hayu and the one that
says the facts were that they were
לויים, Levi'im, קסבר מעלין מדוכן בין ליוחסין בין למעשר. kasavar ma'alin mi-duchan
bein le-yuchasin bein le-ma'aser. If you guys saw
them... So it's sometimes, guess what, important to know the facts. It's
like I spent a whole year teaching יורה דעה Yoreh Deah in
the ישיבה Yeshiva כשרות. Kashrus. I can tell you any ש"ך Shach
and the ט"ז Taz and the פתחי תשובה Pischei Teshuva and רב
משה. Reb Moshe's. Then somebody says, "So Rabbi Winzberg, can I buy
so and so without a הכשר? Hechsher? What's the story with this
acetate? Facts?!"
You gotta ask somebody else.
Okay, but guess what? It matters to know the facts because of
knowing the facts? So okay, so
it matters to know who were, who were the people playing there?
Can I marry into that family? How good is the הכשר Hechsher
on the people that are playing? So that's where it matters. But
it's not a debate of what the הלכה Halacha is. The הלכה
Halacha is that anybody could play a musical instrument because the עיקר
שירה Ikkar Shira was בפה, b'peh, not בכלי. b'khli. Okay, so that's
what the גמרא, Gemara, that's what the גמרא Gemara says emerges from
this debate. And by the way, that's how the רמב"ם Rambam rules
as well. The רמב"ם Rambam rules עיקר שירה Ikkar Shira is בפה
b'peh and that the non לויים Levi'im could play the musical instrument.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, says like this:
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says like this: רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר,
Rebbe Yirmiya bar Abba amar, so that was an attempt to say
that the debate about can you play the musical instruments on שבת
Shabbos was about playing them with the קרבן Korban whether the עיקר
שירה Ikkar Shira was בפה b'peh or בכלי. b'khli. But the גמרא
Gemara anyway sort of says looks like what emerges from this, looks
like everybody should admit that עיקר שירה Ikkar Shira was בפה. b'peh.
So, yeah. We have an answer to this in the נוסח Nusach
of our תפילה, Tefilla, right? היום
שהיו לויים אומרים. Hayom shehayu Levi'im omrim. Oh, you mean שהיו לויים
אומרים. shehayu Levi'im omrim. Yeah, it's interesting, it seems like nobody debates
that the לויים Levi'im were the ones that did the שירה. Shira.
That's quite fascinating, you're right. And the debate is whether they were
the ones that did the music instruments. But it's true even though
the גמרא Gemara still thinks it's possible that עיקר שירה Ikkar Shira
was בכלי b'khli even though they let the שירה Shira still be
the purview like only the לויים, Levi'im, which is true. I mean
it's like just because if A then B doesn't mean if B
then A. Just because it was the לויים Levi'im does not mean
that that was the עיקר. Ikkar. But it is interesting that the
only debate of were there other people that did it was by
the music, not by the singing. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this: רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר, Rebbe Yirmiya bar Abba amar,
so now רבי ירמיה בר אבא אמר Rebbe Yirmiya bar Abba amar
says: מחלוקת בשיר של שואבה. Machloket b'shir shel sho'eva. That debate of
can you play the musical instrument
on שבת, Shabbos, that was a debate about the music that accompanied
or the חליל chalil that accompanied the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat Beit
HaShoeva. רבי
יוסף בר יהודה סבר שמחה יתירה נמי דוחה את השבת. Rebbe Yosef
bar Yehuda savar Simcha yeteira nami docha et HaShabbos. יוסף בר יהודה
Yosef bar Yehuda says I know it's not directly part of the
קרבן, Korban, it's just about having the extra
שמחה, Simcha, ושאבתם מים בששון ushavtem mayim b'sasson etc. but nevertheless שמחה
Simcha in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash that also can be done
on שבת. Shabbos. Again, דוחה את השבת docha et HaShabbos is a
strange term because at the end of the day it's just a
rabbinic problem. Okay, yes even though שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis HaShoeva
but it's in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, that can be done
on שבת. Shabbos. רבנן סברי שמחה יתירה אינו דוחה את השבת. Rabbanan
savri Simcha yeteira eino docha et HaShabbos. No, just for this idea
of having extra joy with the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva,
that does not allow you to play musical instruments on שבת. Shabbos.
That's the debate. אבל בשיר של קרבן, Aval b'shir shel korban, when
it comes to doing the song, the singing that accompanies the קרבן,
Korban, דברי הכל עבודה היא ודוחה את השבת. divrei hakol avoda hi
v'docha et HaShabbos. Everybody would agree that that is an עבודה Avoda
and it overrides שבת Shabbos and therefore everybody would agree that you
could play musical instruments with the קרבנות Korbanot when they are brought
on שבת. Shabbos. Now here the astute person will say: one minute.
Didn't we just seem to conclude a second ago that עיקר שירה
Ikkar Shira was what? בפה. b'peh. Right? And the musical instruments can
even be done by the עבדים avadim etc. etc. And here we're
saying: oh but by the way when it comes to the question
of doing it on שבת, Shabbos, right, everybody says that the playing
the musical instruments is an עבודה avoda and can be done on
שבת. Shabbos. So I thought you said that I mean if done
by the עבדים avadim it's not really an עבודה avoda or whatever
and it's done by the עבדים avadim it's not really an עבודה
avoda and what does it mean that everybody says that the playing
of the musical instrument can be done on שבת? Shabbos? So there
are I would say three answers to this and I think the
best answer is implicit
in the רמב"ם. Rambam. One answer is it doesn't really mean it's
an עבודה. avoda. But it means that let's face it. You're not
dealing with a real שבת Shabbos violation here like I said, it's
a rabbinic issue of playing a musical instrument on שבת. Shabbos. What's
the big deal anyway? So what it just means is okay even
though it's there to accompany the singing and the singing is the
עיקר Ikkar as we said, it's not the music that's the עיקר.
Ikkar. So it's enough part of the עבודה avoda of the
קרבנות, Korbanot, it's really not such a שבת Shabbos problem anyway so
fine it can be done. Okay so that's one explanation that it
doesn't really mean עבודה היא, avoda hi, it just means look it's
not really such a big deal here anyway and we're going to
let when it comes with the קרבן Korban we'll... override שבת. Shabbos.
A second answer which is maybe a variation of the first is
you know can you sort of call it a like part of
the עבודה avoda without saying that the עיקר שירה, ikkar shira, you
know, like maybe this is really just a variation of the first,
but it's really saying like when it's being done, you know, are
you יוצא yotze without the musical instrument? Yes. Does the musical instrument
need to be לויים? Leviim? No. But when they are done, they
are incorporated into the עבודה avoda as opposed to like the music
you play as a שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis Hashoeiva, that's all
like preliminary or that's all like some non-עבודה avoda שמחה simcha that's
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that maybe is about eventually doing
an עבודה avoda but here, it's at the time of the קרבן
korban and it's, you know, it accompanies the singing of the לויים
Leviim so it becomes incorporated into the עבודה. avoda. Okay, so that's
another explanation, but the point is you can allow it to be
done on שבת Shabbos even if it's not really an עבודה avoda
cause at the end of the day anyway we're only dealing with
a rabbinic problem. רמב"ם Rambam says something much more interesting. The רמב"ם
Rambam says that although the playing of the musical instrument is not
an עבודה avoda and can be done by non-לויים, Leviim, he says
when it comes to ימים טובים Yamim Tovim and ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh he says, I mentioned this yesterday, there there's a מצוה מן
התורה mitzvah min hatorah to not only to play music that accompanies
singing, but there's a מצוה מן התורה mitzvah min hatorah to blow
the חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. And that he says can only be done by
the כהנים, kohanim, which is fascinating because we tend to forget about
the חצוצרות chatzotzrot that are in the תורה. Torah. And then right
after saying that there's this biblical מצוה mitzvah to do the חצוצרות
chatzotzrot with קרבנות korbanot
on יום טוב Yom Tov and ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, he says,
and on, this is now basing himself on a משנה mishna elsewhere,
he says, and on basically all the ימים טובים Yamim Tovim there
was a special playing of the חליל, chalil, remember the name of
the פרק, perek, החליל, Hechalil, apparently a musical instrument that was not
played with the singing of the לויים Leviim during, you know, the
normal days, but on יום טוב Yom Tov they would actually play
the חליל chalil to be part of, to accompany the לויים Leviim
and he says, and that is עבודה היא, avoda hi, and that
can only be played by לויים. Leviim. So according to the רמב"ם
Rambam there actually are two levels. There's the general music that accompanies
the singing that comes on a daily basis, and that's not an
עבודה, avoda, that's basically about the singing and anybody could play that.
But for יום טוב, Yom Tov, there was a special use of
a special instrument that was like signified somehow that it was special
because it was יום טוב. Yom Tov. It's interesting to think about
that. It's יום טוב, Yom Tov, we're going to add some special,
you know, people to the orchestra. We're going to have an expanded
orchestra because it's יום טוב. Yom Tov. Not only, and it seems
to be modeled after the idea of חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. So the same
way on יום טוב Yom Tov there's this חצוצרות chatzotzrot that are
by the כהנים, kohanim, again, not accompanying the singing, just making some
blasts, but on יום טוב Yom Tov also we have an expanded
orchestra, and that extra playing, which is I think sort of modeled
or inferred from the idea of the חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, this extra instrument,
that actually is unique to the לויים Leviim and that is an
עבודה. avoda. So it's quite interesting how the רמב"ם Rambam sorts that
out. On the one hand we said עיקר שירה ikkar shira was
בפה, bepeh, and then a sentence later we said oh by the
way, the חליל chalil that was played, you know, the חליל chalil
that was played, that was עיקר עבודה ikkar avoda and therefore it
was דוחה את השבת. doche es Hashabbos. Like every day of the
week? Yes. קרבנות korbanot and לויים Leviim were singing. Yeah. It was
some ragamuffin orchestra playing? Yeah. Right? But on שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב Yom Tov there
was חצוצרות chatzotzrot was also every day? No, חצוצרות chatzotzrot was only
not שבת, Shabbos, יום טוב Yom Tov and ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
Just to add to the שמחה? simcha? Yes. Well, I don't know
why, but because it's in the תורה. Torah. We could have another
discussion about those פסוקים pesukim in the תורה. Torah. Okay, but it
was not part of the singing, right, they would just do independent
חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, and then what you would also do on יום טוב
Yom Tov but not ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, so even a further
subset was that you would add חלילים chalilim to the orchestra. Nice,
I was so, that you didn't know where to look first. Yeah,
exactly. So anyway, but that is I think very interesting because again,
the name of the פרק perek is החליל Hechalil and again, in
elsewhere in, you know, we find that a particular emphasis of the,
you know, in another מסכת masechet of the unique times when they
would use the חליל chalil to accompany the singing of the קרבנות
korbanot and the רמב"ם Rambam actually makes something special about that. It
wasn't just סתם stam let's add some music instruments, but it actually
was specifically a לויים Leviim עבודה avoda even though the normal musical
instruments were not. And that's how the רמב"ם Rambam reads this idea
here. So when non-Orthodox synagogues play musical instruments on שבת Shabbos in
שול? shul?
Yes. Issue is more what it symbolizes in terms of their rejection
of rabbinic authority? I'm not going to get into that. What it
certainly is is that it wasn't the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I
mean here we're talking about within the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. By
the way though, I would say that that reading of the רמב"ם
Rambam might lead to the conclusion that on יום טוב Yom Tov
they did, you know, I said they added instruments to the orchestra.
but it might actually lead to the conclusion that they didn't have
any of the other orchestra instruments of the orchestra, they just had
the חליל. Chalil. Because if you read it that way, meaning the
first way I read it was, okay, it's not such a big
שבת Shabbos problem anyway, so even if עיקר שירה בפה, Ikkar Shira
Bepeh, you can still play some musical instruments on שבת Shabbat when
it comes with the קרבן, korban, okay? But this way of reading
it is no, the normal instruments were not allowed. עיקר שירה בפה.
Ikkar Shira Bepeh. The one thing that they did was just the
חליל. Chalil. So that would be that's like a different image, but
that could emerge from the רמב"ם's Rambam's approach. All right, okay, let's
open those opening lines. Okay, that wasn't for שבת Shabbos and יום
טוב. Yom Tov. All right, so now we move on. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay? מתיבי, Meiseivi, says
the גמרא, Gemara, שיר של שואבה דוחה את השבת דברי רבי יוסי
בר יהודה. Shir Shel Shoeva doche es haShabbos divrei Rabbi Yosei bar
Yehuda. So the song of the שואבה, Shoeva, the whatever, overrides שבת,
Shabbat, that's what רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda says.
וחכמים אומרים אף יום טוב אינו דוחה, Vachachamim omrim af Yom Tov
eino doche, it doesn't even override יום טוב. Yom Tov. So you
see there very clearly that the debate of רבי יוסי בר יהודה
Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda and the חכמים Chachamim was about the music
of the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva, not about the music
that accompanied קרבן. korban. So מאי קשיא, meichasha, the גמרא Gemara says,
תיובתא דרב יוסף תיובתא. Tiyuvta deRabbi Yosef tiyuvta. That's a complete contradiction
of רב יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, it shows that who said that the
debate was only about the normal it was about the instruments of
שבת Shabbat of the normal קרבן korban that came with the קרבן.
korban. Here you see it's about the instruments of the שמחת בית
השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva. So the גמרא Gemara says, לימא בשיר של
שואבה הוא דפליגי אבל בשיר של קרבן דברי הכל דוחה את השבת?
leima beshir shel shoeva hu depeiligi aval beshir shel korban divrei hakol
doche es haShabbos? So it sounds like, says the גמרא, Gemara, to
that A, they debate whether you can do musical instruments during the
שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva, and it would sound also perhaps
you could infer as well that when it came to the normal
music that accompanied קרבנות, korbanos, everybody would agree that that could be
done on שבת, Shabbat, right? It sounds like they're only debating whether
you can do it for the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva.
So לימא תהוי תיובתא דרב יוסף בתרתי? leima tehavei tiyuvta deRabbi Yosef
betarti? So maybe it contradicts both aspects of רב יוסף, Rabbi Yosef,
meaning רב יוסף Rabbi Yosef said they are debating the music with
קרבנות, korbanos, and everybody agrees with שואבה Shoeva is off limits. Here
it says they're debating שואבה. Shoeva. But it seems so that A
shows that not everybody agrees שואבה Shoeva is a problem, but it
also seems to imply that everybody agrees קרבנות korbanos is okay, which
contradicts his other statement that he says they debate קרבנות. korbanos. So
the גמרא Gemara says no. אמר לך רב יוסף, Amar lecha Rabbi
Yosef, רב יוסף Rabbi Yosef would say to you, פליגי בשיר של
שואבה והוא הדין לקרבן. peligi beshir shel shoeva vehu hadin lekorban. No,
they debate both issues. Can you play, can you do it for
the שואבה Shoeva and can you do it with the קרבנות? korbanos?
Again, on שבת. Shabbat. והדר קמיפלגי בשיר של שואבה, Vehadar kamiflegi beshir
shel shoeva, so why are they focusing on the שמחת בית השואבה?
Simchas Beis HaShoeva? להודיע כחו דרבי יוסי בר יהודה, Lehodia' kocho deRabbi
Yosei bar Yehuda, to show you the strength of רבי יוסי בר
יהודה's Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda's position, דאפילו דשואבה נמי דוחה, de'afilu deShoeva
nami doche, not only does he allow you to play on שבת
Shabbat with the קרבן, korban, he allows you to play on שבת
Shabbat even for the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva. But maybe
it's not a complete contradiction to רב יוסף, Rabbi Yosef, maybe they
debate both issues. The גמרא Gemara says no, it doesn't sound like
that. It sounds like they only debate שואבה. Shoeva. How do you
know that? Because of the following. The גמרא Gemara says והא קתני,
veha katani, our משנה Mishna says, זהו חליל של בית השואבה, zehu
chalil shel beis hashoeva,
this issue that we're talking about that the music can't be on
שבת Shabbat and on יום טוב, Yom Tov, that is the flute
of the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva, שאינו דוחה לא את
השבת ולא את היום טוב. she'eino doche lo es haShabbos velo es
haYom Tov. It doesn't override שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So the גמרא Gemara says what's the implication of that line, זהו?
zehu? This is the one that doesn't override שבת Shabbat and יום
טוב. Yom Tov. So זהו דאינו דוחה, zehu de'eino doche,
this flute doesn't override שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom Tov. אבל
דקרבן דוחה, Aval dekorban doche, the strong implication of the משנה Mishna
is there's another flute, the one that comes with the קרבנות, korbanot,
that's דוחה, doche, that does override שבת Shabbat and יום טוב. Yom
Tov. So מאני, mani, who is the author of this משנה Mishna
that says yes it overrides, no it doesn't override on שמחת בית
השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva, yes it overrides by קרבן? korban?
מאני? Mani? אי נימא רבי יוסי בר יהודה, Ineima Rabbi Yosei bar
Yehuda, if it's רבי יוסי בר יהודה, Rabbi Yosei bar Yehuda, הא
אמר שיר של שואבה נמי דוחה. ha'amar shir shel shoeva nami doche.
He says that you can play the music instruments even on שבת
Shabbat for שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva. אלא לאו רבנן, Ela
lav Rabbanan, it must be the רבנן, Rabbis, who we know say
you can't play it for שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva. And
you see that the רבנן Rabbis who say you can't play it
in שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis HaShoeva, and that's what they say
in our משנה, Mishna, said זהו, zehu, this is the one you
don't play on שבת, Shabbat, which means that the קרבן korban one
you do play on שבת. Shabbat. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
אלא לאו רבנן, ela lav Rabbanan, ותיובתא דרב יוסף בתרתי תיובתא. vutiyuvta
deRabbi Yosef betarti tiyuvta. It's a double contradiction of רב יוסף. Rabbi
Yosef. Number one, you see that רבי יוסי בר יהודה Rabbi Yosei
bar Yehuda says you can play it on שבת Shabbat even for
שמחת בית השואבה. Simchas Beis HaShoeva. And number two, you see that
everybody agrees that when it comes to the קרבן korban you can
play, everyone agrees you can play it on שבת. Shabbat. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר עיקר שירה בכלי? mai
ta'ama demanda amar ikkar shira bichli? Now to get back to that
debate, what's the reason of the one that says the basic שירה
shira is the music? דכתיב, Dichtiv, as the verse says, ויאמר חזקיהו
להעלות העלה להמזבח, vayomer Chizkiyahu leha'alot ha'ola lehamizbeach, חזקיהו Chizkiyahu said
to bring the burnt offering on the altar. ובעת החל העלה, Uve'eis
hechel ha'ola, and when the עולה ola was beginning to be burnt,
החל שיר השם, hechel shir Hashem, the song of God began. The
song actually comes at the pouring of the wine, which came when
the קרבן korban was being offered. Not in this
פסוק, pasuk, והחצצרות, v'hachatzotzros, the song of God and the trumpets, על
ידי כלי דויד מלך ישראל, al yedei klei Dovid melech Yisrael, with
the instruments of David king of Israel. Interesting if so associating them
with King David. Why? So therefore you see that it says that
the song began and then it mentioned the music. So you see
the word song here, right, what does שיר shir mean in the
Torah? Does שיר shir have a lot of meanings, could mean poetry,
could mean song, could mean music. So it says here you see
it's using the word שיר shir with the קרבן korban and says
the שיר shir began and they began playing the music instruments. So
שיר shir means the music. That's what שיר shir is, it's the
music. Okay, מאי טעמא דמאן דאמר עיקר שירה בפה? mai ta'ama d'man
d'amar ikar shira b'peh? What's the reason if you say it's basically
the song?
So דכתיב, d'ksiv, the verse
says, ויהי כאחד למחצצרים ולמשוררים להשמיע קול אחד. vayehi k'echad l'm'chatz'tz'rim v'lam'shorerim
l'hashmia kol echad. It was as one those playing on the trumpets
and those giving forth song to make one sound. So משוררים, m'shorerim,
so we would read it like the accompaniment of the חצצרות chatzotzros
with the song. But again what the גמרא gemara here is saying
is it's interesting, right? At some degree it's also saying that it's
a, it's a question of terminology. Meaning not just like, okay, the
way it's usually famous is what was central, was it the song
or the music? Here it's almost saying like, what does the word
שיר shir mean? Is the basic use of the word שיר shir
in the context of קרבן, korban, does that mean singing or does
that mean music? So the first verse indicated that the word שיר
shir meant music. This verse says that, I'm sorry, that the word,
yeah, meant music. This verse, this verse is saying is understanding that
the word, that the combination of the מחצצרים m'chatz'tz'rim and the משוררים
m'shorerim somehow understands that it means that the חצצרות chatzotzros are accompanying
the singing and the word שירה shira means song.
So רש''י Rashi says now why, רש''י Rashi sort of says why
is that? I mean, why can't we say, you know, it means
that the music combined with the חצצרות? chatzotzros? So רש''י Rashi again
makes the point that I mentioned before with the רמב''ם, Rambam, trumpets
are not musical instruments that like that, you know, that sort of
blend in with other musical instruments. Okay, trumpets come by themselves. Okay,
so that was the whole point I made before about the רמב''ם.
Rambam. So when it says
למחצצרים ולמשוררים, l'm'chatz'tz'rim v'lam'shorerim, it means those were two that they weren't
like a blending of musical instruments. It was trumpets and משוררים, m'shorerim,
so it's understanding that that's independent and that שירה shira means singing.
Okay, though I don't know, not so explicit, but that's how the
גמרא gemara is getting it. So that shows you
עיקר שירה בפה. ikar shira b'peh. ואידך נמי הכתיב, v'idach nami hach'ksiv,
what about the verse that said that mentioned the music together with
שיר shir and sounded like that שיר shir was the music? So
the גמרא gemara says, הכי קאמר החל שיר ה' בפה על ידי
כלי דוד מלך ישראל בבסומי קלא. hachi ka'amar hechel shir Hashem b'peh
al yedei klei Dovid melech Yisrael b'busumei kala. Yes, there was a
focus there or there was a talk there about the instruments, but
it meant the instruments were accompanying the singing, not that the שיר
shir was the instrument.
ואידך נמי הכתיב ויהי כאחד למחצצרים ולמשוררים, v'idach nami hach'ksiv vayehi k'echad
l'm'chatz'tz'rim v'lam'shorerim, somehow the word משוררים m'shorerim very much suggests to the
גמרא gemara the idea of singing, not the idea of music.
הכי קאמר משוררים דומיא דמחצצרים, hachi ka'amar m'shorerim dumya d'm'chatz'tz'rim, and now
it finally takes a step back. You know what? Maybe not. Maybe
the word משוררים m'shorerim just like the word מחצצרים, m'chatz'tz'rim, people playing
the
trumpet, מה מחצצרים בכלי אף משוררים בכלי, mah m'chatz'tz'rim b'kli af m'shorerim
b'kli, maybe it means that the same way the word מחצצרים m'chatz'tz'rim
means trumpet players, משוררים m'shorerim doesn't mean singers, maybe משוררים m'shorerim means
players of musical instruments. Okay, so the גמרא gemara ends with a
question, but again I want to point out what's fascinating, which is
back and forth we say is עיקר שירה בכלי עיקר שירה בפה.
ikar shira b'kli ikar shira b'peh. The conclusion seems to be עיקר
שירה בפה. ikar shira b'peh. But again we sort of said, but
you can play, we also concluded very strongly that it seems very
clear that you can play musical instruments with the קרבנות korbanos on
שבת Shabbos and at the same time עיקר שירה בפה. ikar shira
b'peh. So again how does that balance out? And I'll just remind
you of the three points I said. One is, okay, it's not
such a problem playing musical instruments anyway, it's only דרבנן, d'rabanan, I
mean not, but in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash it's not such
a problem, it's דרבנן d'rabanan so, okay, it doesn't have to be
such an עבודה. avodah. Or the other is like, okay, when it's
done it's incorporated as we said, it accompanies the song and it
becomes like the עבודה avodah and so on and that gives it
enough weight, so maybe those are two variations of a similar idea.
And the third is the fascinating idea of the רמב''ם Rambam that
there was a separate status to the musical instruments that they played
on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. That the normal music
was not an
עבודה avodah but on יום טוב, Yom Tov, on יום טוב Yom
Tov it was played with the חליל, chalil, that was an עבודה
avodah and that was only לוים Leviyim and that had a special
status and that was what was דוחה docheh and allowed to be
played. Yes. I want to ask about the language שמחת בית השואבה,
Simchas Beis Hashoeivah, was it standard structure? No,
no, we're going to get to the description right now but no.
I mean, it's a good point, why does it say שמחת בית
השואבה, Simchas Beis Hashoeivah, not if you have the גירסא girsa of
שמחת בית חשובה Simchas Beis Chashuvah like the גמרא gemara says, so
that's different.
Yeah, I don't know. I don't know why the word בית Bayis
there. It's a good question.
Yeah, I mean, it's obviously because it connects to the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, but there's no physical structure. Let's take a look now
as we get to actually discussing the שמחת בית השואבה. Simchat Beis
Hashoeva. Okay, so משנה: Mishnah: מי שלא ראה שמחת בית השואבה לא
ראה שמחה מימיו. Mishelo ra'ah simchat beit hashoeva lo ra'ah simcha miyamav.
If you've never seen the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchat Beis Hashoeva, you've
never really seen a good Jewish
שמחה. simcha. Okay, what a real party is. במוצאי יום טוב הראשון
של חג, Bemotzei yomtov harishon shel chag,
now again, we just got through saying that they would not do
it the night on יום טוב yomtov and שבת. Shabbos. So I
mean, on the one hand, it could be noted that we've been
talking about when they played the musical instruments. But the other thing
that you couldn't do on שבת, Shabbos, of course, was you couldn't
carry the water. You had to draw it from before. But in
theory, you could have done a שמחת בית השואבה Simchas Beis Hashoeva
the first night of יום טוב, yomtov, because you can carry on
יום טוב yomtov and you can go ahead and you can party
throughout the night without the musical instruments. Okay, but this משנה mishnah
seems to suggest that when you say you didn't play the musical
instruments for the שמחת בית השואבה, Simchas Beis Hashoeva, it also meant
you basically didn't have the party. Right, that's never said explicitly, but
that's interesting. Would they have a party at all the first night
of יום טוב? yomtov? This משנה mishnah makes it pretty clear the
answer is no. They would start the partying, you know, only מוצאי
יום טוב Motzei Yomtov and that's when you could bring in the
musical instruments. Okay, so that just shows you that if there's no
music, no party. So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this, משנה:
Mishnah: okay, so במוצאי יום
טוב הראשון של חג, Bemotzei yomtov harishon shel chag, so the first
night following יום טוב, yomtov, ירדו לעזרת נשים, yardu l'ezrat nashim, so
they would go down into the women's section, ומתקנים שם תיקון גדול,
u'metaknim sham tikkun gadol, and they fix it up real nice. Okay,
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what that means, fix it up
real nice. מנורות של זהב היו שם, Menorot shel zahav hayu sham,
and they would because the women's section basically served, or the women's
עזרה azara courtyard basically served as a type of a social hall.
Okay, and that's where sort of everybody gathered before going into the
actual עזרה azara and the bringing of the קרבן. korban. So that's
what they used, they used the social hall for the party. Okay.
So מנורות של זהב היו שם. menorot shel zahav hayu sham. There
were golden candle מנורות, menorahs, candelabras. I mean, not technically like obviously
not, you know, like the מנורה menorah in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash itself, maybe evocative of it, but anyway, but whatever they were,
they were huge candelabras. וארבעה ספלים של זהב בראשיהם, V'arba'ah s'falim shel
zahav b'rosheihem, and they had four big funnels of gold at their
heads, which might mean that there were only a four branched מנורה,
menorah, maybe it means the funnels, I don't know, fed to other
all of the branches. וארבעה סולמות לכל אחד ואחד, V'arba'ah sulamot l'chol
echad v'echad, and each funnel had four ladders leading up to it.
You can obviously realize that this is a little bit stylized and
not exactly literal. Okay anyway, וארבעה ילדים. v'arba'ah yeladim. What? They translate
it as bowls. Bowls. Okay, well I guess it's a difference about
whether you're seeing the funnels feeding into a receptacle or whether they
actually are the receptacle. Yeah, so bowls might be a better translation.
Like streetlamps. Yeah, okay. Right. Photograph. Right. Okay,
so bowls might be better because it seems like this means it
is the receptacle and it was maybe like a four branched candelabra.
וארבעה סולמות לכל אחד ואחד, V'arba'ah sulamot l'chol echad v'echad, four ladders
leading up to each one of the bowls. וארבעה ילדים מפרחי כהונה,
V'arba'ah yeladim mipirchei kehunah, and four of the young either children or
young men of the
כהנים, Kohanim, ובידיהם כדים, u'v'yadeihem kadim, you know, went up, maybe each
ladder or four, one per ladder. ובידיהם כדים שמאה ועשרים לוג, U'v'yadeihem
kadim sheme'ah v'esrim log, and each one had a pitcher of 120
לוג. log. Now let's think how big that is.
A לוג log is about 12 ounces, 14 ounces.
So 120 of that is
1400, 280, about 1700 ounces. Okay, I don't know, what does that
translate into in terms of gallon -- how many ounces in a
gallon -- 64 ounces in a gallon?
128 ounces in a gallon. 128. And how much did I just
say this would be? 1700ish. 1700.
So what, like 15 gallons?
Do you think do you think a kid, even a young man,
could carry 15 gallons in one of those jugs from like, you
know, water that you get, the mineral water, those big jugs. Think
about a gallon of milk. Think about trying to get 15 of
them. How many ounces לוג log is? 14.
1680 divided by what?
What'd we say, 128?
128 ounces to a gallon is 13.
13 gallons. 13 gallons. Okay. All right, I don't think this is
literal. All right. Okay, 120 לוג log שהן מטילין לכל ספל וספל,
shehein matilin l'chol sefal v'sefal, that went into, maybe it meant multiple
pitchers, multiple trips, you know anyway, and that they ultimately each bowl
contained, contained, you know, 17 or whatever it was, 15, 14 gallons.
מבלאי מכנסי כהנים ומהמיהם, Miblaei michnesei kohanim u'mehemeihem, from the worn-out strips
of the used out...
underwear and belts of the כהנים, kohanim, מהם
היו מפקיעין, meheim hayu mafki'in, I'm sorry, from the worn out clothing
of the כהנים, kohanim, מהם היו מפקיעין, meheim hayu mafki'in, from them
they would make strips ובהן היו מדליקין u'vahen hayu madlikin and they
would use those as wicks and from there they would use those
to light in the bowls. ולא היה חצר בירושלים שאינה מאירה מאור
בית השואבה. V'lo hayah chatzer b'Yerushalayim she'eina me'ira me'ohr beit hasho'eiva. There
was no courtyard in all of Jerusalem that was not lit up
from the light coming from this rejoicing of the בית
השואבה. Beit Hasho'eiva. חסידים ואנשי מעשה היו מרקדים בפניהם Chasidim v'anshei ma'aseh
hayu merakdim bifneihem and righteous people and people of deeds would be
dancing בפניהם bifneihem in front of them, and addressing who the them
are, in front of everybody I guess, ואבוקות של אור שבידיהם va'avukot
shel or she'b'yadeihem with torches of light or torches of
fire. Okay, and ואומרים לפניהם דברי תשבחות v'omrim lifneihem divrei tishbachot and
would say as they're juggling these torches would be singing, saying praises
and songs. Nice little description in רש"י Rashi of trying to describe
what juggling is. So look at רש"י Rashi ואבוקות של אור. va'avukot
shel or. רש"י Rashi says: זורקין אותן כלפי מעלה, zorkin otan klapei
ma'alah, you'd throw them up into the air ומקבלין אותן u'mekablin otan
and you'd receive
it, ויש שבקיאין לעשות כן בארבע אבוקות או בשמונה וזורק זו ומקבל
זו וזורק זו ומקבל זו. v'yesh she'b'ki'in la'asot kein b'arba avukot o
b'shmoneh v'zorek zo u'mekabel zo v'zorek zo u'mekabel zo. So it's just
a little description of how to of juggling. Okay, anyway. והלוים בכנורות
ובנבלים ובמצלתים ובחצוצרות ובכלי שיר בלא מספר V'halevi'im b'chinorot u'vinvalim u'v'metziltayim u'v'chatzotzrot
u'v'chelei shir v'lo mispar and the לוים Levi'im were playing all these
different types of musical instruments, cymbals and flutes and trumpets. על חמישה
עשר מעלות היורדות מעזרת ישראל לעזרת נשים Al chamisha asar ma'alot hayordot
me'ezrat Yisrael l'ezrat nashim on the 15 steps that went down from
the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael to the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim כנגד
חמישה עשר מעלות או שירי המעלות שבתהלים k'neged chamisha asar ma'alot o
shirei hama'alot she'b'Tehillim corresponding to the 15 songs of ascent in תהלים,
Tehillim, there were 15 steps of ascent going from עזרת נשים Ezrat
Nashim to עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. שעליהם לוים עומדים בכלי שיר ואומרים
שירה. She'aleihem Levi'im omdim b'chelei shir v'omrim shirah. On those the לוים
Levi'im would be
stand and with their musical instruments and do their singing. Now of
course the question is, we just got through talking about the singing
of the לוים Levi'im and the playing of the musical instruments that
would accompany the קרבנות. korbanot. But this wasn't, if you think about
how things look,
right, I'll do a side view,
so this is
the 15 steps, okay, so this is עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim,
right, this is עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, there'd be a like a
whole gate there to get in. Okay, so right, so this is
שער ניקנור Sha'ar Nikanor or whatever.
So this is your gate. Okay and then here you have, I
mean עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael is small but whatever, but anyway and
then you have the עזרת כהנים Ezrat Kohanim and you got your
מזבח mizbe'ach and you've got your whole thing, right? What? This is
north, west, south, east, fine. So now that's our next excavation... you
come, right, you come through here, you go up, you go through
שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nikanor, right, you got it? Yes? Okay. So anyway,
okay, so here's where they have their party, right, and here, right,
is where you have the steps leading down, so they would be
standing here, everybody would be partying here, the band would be in
the front, okay basically, and they'd be standing and singing here and
everybody would be here having their party. So the question is if
this is where the לוים Levi'im stood with their music and their
song and the קרבנות korbanot are being brought here doesn't exactly work,
right, and you got a wall here, you got whatever, so basically
רש"י Rashi says this is not where the דוכן, dukhan, this is
not where they stood for the קרבנות, korbanot, where they stood for
the קרבנות korbanot to play the song and to play the music
and the song was over here, and as we've said it wasn't
necessarily the לוים Levi'im playing the music, but don't confuse as רש"י
Rashi where they're standing here for the party to where they would
stand for the קרבנות. korbanot. Okay. All right, so okay, now okay
ועמדו שני כהנים בשער העליון שיורד מעזרת ישראל
לעזרת נשים. va'amdu shnei kohanim b'sha'ar ha'elyon she'yored me'ezrat Yisrael l'ezrat nashim.
So now two כהנים kohanim stood at the top of the steps,
at this gate that basically would go, would lead out of עזרת
ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and then you'd go down the steps to go
to עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim as I just demonstrated. ושתי חצוצרות בידיהם
u'shnei chatzotzrot b'yadeihem and they would have two trumpets in their hands.
קרא הגבר, karah hagever,
then the cock crowed, so it was beginning to be daybreak, wasn't
sunrise yet. תקעו והריעו ותקעו, teki'u v'heri'u v'teki'u, they did תקיעה תרועה
תקיעה, teki'ah teru'ah teki'ah, we've already mentioned תקיעה תרועה תקיעה teki'ah teru'ah
teki'ah before that would accompany the pouring of the wine of the
water, we mentioned תקיעה תרועה תקיעה teki'ah teru'ah teki'ah that would accompany
the waving of
the whole ערבה aravah ritual. So here you had a תקיעה תרועה
תקיעה, teki'ah teru'ah teki'ah, but this was more for the שמחה simcha
that preceded and they would do that when they're starting to ready
because what they're about to do you understand is they partied throughout
the night and then at daybreak they did a whole big procession
to draw the water, so that was the שואבה, sho'eiva, they actually
did the drawing of the water, it culminated... the drawing of the
water then bring the water into the המקדש Mikdash and doing the
pouring. So when they to begin the procession, to transition from the
party to begin the procession, they did the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה Tkiyah
Teruah Tkiyah at the top of the steps.
Okay, הגיעו למעלה עשירית, Higi'u lema'ala asiri, they got to the tenth
step going down, whether it means which way are you counting ten,
anyway, תקעו והריעו ותקעו, taku veheriu vetaku, they did another תקיעה תרועה
תקיעה. Tkiyah Teruah Tkiyah. הגיעו לעזרה, Higi'u la'azara, then they got to
the actual courtyard itself, the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. תקעו והריעו ותקעו,
Taku veheriu vetaku, they did תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. Tkiyah Teruah Tkiyah. Okay,
people take out that next line, it isn't in the משנה Mishna
and anyway because it's redundant because they're already at the עזרה, Azara,
so we'll just skip the next line. היו תוקעים והולכים עד שמגיעים
לשער היוצא ממזרח Hayu toke'im veholechim ad shemagi'im lesha'ar hayotzei mimizrach and
they kept on doing תקיעה תרועה תקיעה Tkiyah Teruah Tkiyah until they
came to the gate leading out of עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim and
היוצא ממזרח, hayotzei mimizrach, okay, until they led to the easternmost gate.
And then you're going from here, right here you are, you're on
Temple Mount, right, so you're going to go here, you're going to
go down Temple Mount and you're going to go
out to the
שילוח. Shiloach. Okay, הפכו פניהם ממזרח למערב. Hafchu pneihem mimizrach lema'arav. Now
when they got to the east gate out of עזרת נשים, Ezrat
Nashim, they turned their face back facing facing west ואמרו ve'amru and
they said, looking at the בית המקדש: Beis Hamikdash: אבותינו שהיו במקום
הזה, Avoteinu shehayu bamakom hazeh, our forefathers that were in this place,
meaning in the בית ראשון, Bayis Rishon, who אחוריהם אל ההיכל, achoreihem
el haheichal, this is actually a description that we find in the
תנ"ך Tanach about what was done in the בית ראשון Bayis Rishon
by when they were עובדי עבודה זרה: ovdei avodah zarah: אחוריהם אל
ההיכל, achoreihem el haheichal, they would have their backs facing the היכל
Heichal ופניהם קדמה ufneihem kedma and their front to the east ומשתחוים
קדמה לשמש umishtachavim kedma lashemesh and they would bow down east to
the sun, they would be rejecting the temple and worshipping the sun,
ואנו va'anu but we, ליה l'Yah we are to God, ואנו ליה
עינינו, va'anu l'Yah eineinu, to God is our eyes. רבי יהודה אומר
Rabbi Yehuda omer היו שונים ואומרים hayu shonim ve'omerim and they would
repeat it and say אנו ליה anu l'Yah we are to God
וליה עינינו u'l'Yah eineinu and our eyes are to God. Now that's
all quite fascinating, right, because it's like
why evoke specifically that at this moment? I mean it's one thing
to say you don't walk out of the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
with your back to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you turn around
and you walk backwards. Why to evoke, you know, the contrast of
אבותינו Avoteinu and the way we are? Also to if you remember
also like when it did the whole thing about the הושענא רבה,
Hoshana Rabba, יופי לך מזבח יופי לך מזבח, yofi lach mizbe'ach yofi
lach mizbe'ach, all of this like personification, you know, and sort of
talking, you know, it's making these declarations. I don't know the answer,
I'm just saying it's quite fascinating, like you normally don't find that,
like in the middle of the עבודה avodah making a point: 'I'd
like to make a point here,' you know, or whatever it is,
it's quite fascinating. Yes, yes, it's the thread of that, like the
thread that comes from the תפילין, Tefillin, from the אגדה, Agata, from
the from the and the angel of the מילואים. Milu'im. Yeah, yeah,
yeah, I'm not talking about, I know, but I'm talking about making
a declaration, you know, or or like when they said it said
at the end of like יום Yom at the הושענא רבה, Hoshana
Rabba, יופי לך מזבח יופי לך מזבח, yofi lach mizbe'ach yofi lach
mizbe'ach, right, לקולו, l'kolo, what's that about? I don't know. Parallels to
the הגדה. Haggadah. What? Parallels to the הגדה. Haggadah. Interesting. Our fathers
were
idol worshippers... Yeah, that's true, bringing like a narrative into
this story, the same way you have a narrative into the הגדה.
Haggadah. You're saying that they speak to inanimate objects. Yeah,
yeah, well, right, I mean here they're sort of speaking to no
one, they're
saying אבותינו היו, Avoteinu hayu, ליה מזבח, l'Yah mizbe'ach, whatever that was
more speaking to the altar.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan: מי שלא ראה שמחת בית השואבה לא ראה
שמחה מימיו. mi shelo ra'ah simchat beit hasho'eivah lo ra'ah simcha miyamav.
מי שלא ראה ירושלים בתפארתה לא ראה. mi shelo ra'ah Yerushalayim betif'artah
lo ra'ah. So now that we're talking about how amazing the שמחת
בית השואבה Simchat Beit Hasho'eivah is, let's talk about other things that
were, oh, if you'd only seen it it was so amazing. If
you had not seen Jerusalem in its glory, לא ראה כרך נחמד
מעולם, lo ra'ah krach nechmad me'olam, you've never seen an amazing city.
You might think, you know, Rome or whatever, Paris, yeah, you don't
know anything, you know,
true glory was what ירושלים Yerushalayim used to be like. מי שלא
ראה בית המקדש בבנינו לא ראה בנין מפואר מעולם, mi shelo ra'ah
Beis Hamikdash bevinyano lo ra'ah binyan mefo'ar me'olam, if you've never saw
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash when it was really built, you've never
saw anything. Taj Mahal, that's all, you know, secular beauty. You haven't
really seen real beauty unless you've seen the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
What? Okay, fine, not Jewish
religious. Okay, anyway. מאי היא? Mai hi?
So, so now but it's quite fascinating, I mean I was sort
of trying to give a nice religious spin on this, but the
גמרא Gemara is actually going to try to explain in very physical
and aesthetic ways what was so beautiful about the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. מאי היא? Mai hi? What's this amazing thing about it? So
אמר אביי ואיתימא רב חסדא, amar Abaye ve'isayma Rav Chisda, or which
one first of all are we talking about, first or second? זה
בנין הורדוס, Zeh binyan Hordus, it was the second one and when
it was הורדוס Hordus who actually like, you know, improved the second
one. במאי בנייה? Be'mai banyei? And with what did he build it?
אמר רבא באבני שישא ומרמרא, amar Rava be'avnei shaisha u'marmara, with marble
and מרמרא marmara which רש"י Rashi says is like a black, excuse
me, a white marble. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some
say... in and out, like
you know they do that sometimes like on like facades, right, you
know, alternate so whatever, oh and out, כי היכי דליקבל סידא, ki
heichi d'likabel sida, and that way it could be accept the plaster
I guess, you know, because if it's, you know, that's why you
do it like certainly when you do it on the horizontal plane
like when you lay bricks, like you don't lay them one top
of another, right, you what do you call you alternate or whatever.
Anyway,
okay. סבר למשעיין בדהבא, savar lemishayein bedahava, then he thought that he
was going to be like coat it with gold. אמרו ליה רבנן,
amru lei rabanan, the rabbis said to him, right, getting the rabbis
right up there with Herod, like right in their conversation with Herod,
okay, שבקיה, shabkieh, no you know what leave it the way it
is, דהכי שפיר טפי, de-hachi shapir tfei, it's better this way, דמיחזי
כי אדוותא דימא, de-michzei ke-advata de-yama, it looks like waves of the
sea. You know you got blue and white and jutting in and
out and it looks very beautiful, looks very peaceful, looks like waves
of the sea. That maybe was the only time he ever listened
to rabbis. Yeah. תניא, Tanya, we learned in a Baraita, רבי יהודה
אומר, Rebbi Yehuda omer, מי שלא ראה דיופלוסטין mi shelo ra'ah dyoplostin
של
אלכסנדריא של מצרים, shel Alexandriya shel Mitzrayim, if you never saw the
דיופלוסטין, dyoplostin,
which is clearly some Greek word, does the Gemara tell you what
that word means?
From some Greek word meaning double and colonnade. That's what רש"י Rashi
says. So he's okay. So רש"י Rashi says so it's some double
colonnade, some
huge Coliseum that had with a double colonnade, but actually we're going
to find out it was basically a שול, shul, a huge Coliseum
that was used as a synagogue in Alexandria in Egypt, לא ראה
בכבודן של ישראל, lo ra'ah be-chivodan shel Yisrael, you haven't seen, now
this is an interesting shift, not you haven't seen a gorgeous שול,
shul, but you haven't seen the glory of the Jewish people because
of how many of what that was like to be in that
שול. shul. Okay, what does that mean? אמרו, Amru, they said, כמין
בסילקי גדולה היתה, kemin basilki gedola hayta, it was like a huge
Basilica, a huge like a castle, סטיו לפנים מסטיו, stav lifnim mi-stav,
a double stoa,
פעמים שהיו בה, pe'amim she-hayu bah, and there were times or that
there were more now. Rashi says שישים ריבוא על שישים ריבוא, shishim
ribo al shishim ribo, sixty thousand times sixty, sixty hundred thousand times
sixty hundred thousand, which is I don't even know how much, thirty-six
billion or something. The actual גרסא girsa is שישים ריבוא
shishim ribo or or double כפליים kiflayim or either 1.2 million
or 600,000, not 600,000 times 600,000. כפליים כיוצאי מצרים, kiflayim ke-yotzei mitzrayim,
double those that left Egypt. There were 1.2 million Jews there. Charlie
you'll probably tell us that there weren't 1.2 million people in the
world at that time. No, there were. There were, maybe, at most.
Roman Empire population estimate about 50 million. 50 million? Really? Okay, there
was nowhere there was 1.2 million Jews, I'll tell you that. והיו
בה ע"א קתדראות של זהב, ve-hayu bah ayin-alef katedra'ot shel zahav, and
there were 71 cathedras of gold, meaning golden seats, כנגד ע"א קתדראות
או ע"א של סנהדרי גדולה, keneged ayin-alef katedra'ot o ayin-alef shel sanhedri
gedola, corresponding to the 71 members of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. כל אחת
ואחת אינה פחותה מעשרים ואחד, kol achat ve-achat eina pechuta me-esrim ve-echad,
now again the word ריבוא ribo is a later addition, it should
be no seat was less than 21 ככרי זהב kikrei zahav talents
of gold, but if that wasn't enough of an exaggeration, it's not
21 talents of gold, it was 21 times ten thousand, 210,000 talents
of gold. So anyway, you know, you gotta keep your exaggerations in
the realm of realistic. So it's like that story that these חסידים
chasidim are debating how great their רבי rebbe is. So one says
my רבי rebbe is so great that he can stand on a
bench and see from one end of the world to the next.
And the other guy says why does he have to stand on
a bench? It's that he wants to do his נס בדרך טבע.
nes bederech teva.
So anyway, we have to, so you know, let's keep our exaggerations
within some reasonable limits here. Okay, 1.2 million, not 1.2 billion, 21,000,
21, not 210,000. Anyway, 21 talents of gold. ובימה של עץ באמצעיתה,
u-vima shel etz be-emtzayita, and there was a
wooden בימה bimah in the middle of the synagogue, in the middle
of this like coliseum, וחזן הכנסת עומד עליה, ve-chazzan ha-knesset omed aleha,
and the חזן chazzan here which is not the, it's not the
שליח ציבור, shliach tzibbur, it's the the sexton, the גבאי, gabbai, would
stand on this platform, meaning the point of the platform is not
necessarily where the דאבנינג davening took place, it just made him very
high, very visible. He would stand on a high platform in the
middle, וסודרין בידו, ve-sudarin beyado, and he had like flags in his
hands like the guys that signal the planes. וכיון שהגיעו לענות אמן,
ve-keivan she-higiu la'anot amen, when it was a time to say אמן,
amen, nobody can hear, right? I mean a huge whatever, how can
you hear everything that was said? So הלה מניף בסודר, hala menif
be-sudar, so this guy would do the waving, you know, maybe different
waving for different parts of the דאבנינג. davening. וכל העם עונים אמן,
ve-chol ha-am onim amen, and then everybody could say אמן amen because
you couldn't hear anything but at least you would be able you
would know when to say אמן. amen. Answer אמן amen to a
ברכה. berakhah. Oh, so those that ask an interesting question, can you
infer from here that if you said אמן amen at the end
of
a
This is in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. No, in Alexandria in
Egypt. Right, this huge synagogue, okay. Right, and they're doing this waving
or whatever. Okay. ולא היו יושבים מעורבים, V'lo hayu yoshvim me'uravim, and
it's not like they would be mixed seated. Now, it's like, oh,
this is gonna be a source for separate seating? No, the source
for מחיצה Mechitza is gonna be tomorrow. Okay. But here מעורבים me'uravim
means something else. They wouldn't have mixed seating. אלא זהבים בפני עצמן,
Ella zehavim bifnei atzman, goldsmiths in one area. כספים בפני עצמן, Kesafim
bifnei atzman, silversmiths in another area. ונפחים בפני עצמן, Venafachim bifnei atzman,
and the ironsmiths in a different area. ותרסיים בפני עצמן, Vetarsiyim bifnei
atzman, and coppersmiths in another area. וגרדיים בפני עצמן, Vegardiyim bifnei atzman,
and weavers in their section. וכשאני נכנס שם, Uchshe'ani nichnas sham, and
like, you know what we talk about like how you shouldn't be
shmoozing in שול shul or whatever. You know, actually it's quite fascinating
because they've done lots of studies on ancient synagogues and there was
major function of the synagogue was a social gathering place, you know?
So actually, so it says, actually it's a good way to, you
know, it's like to do business, is you know, that's where you,
you know, find the people you need to be talking to. So
here it was very helpful because they, you would know which section
to go to. וכשאני נכנס שם היה מכיר בעלי אומנתו. Uchshe'ani nichnas
sham haya makir ba'alei umnato. So here's he would be, you know,
you need somebody to hire you on to be an assistant for
a silversmith. So you go to the silversmith section. ונפנה לשם, Venifneh
l'sham, and you go there, משם פרנסתו ופרנסת אנשי ביתו. misham parnasato
u-parnasat anshei beito. And look at the מדת חסד midat chessed that
came out of there. You know, doing business is a מצוה, mitzvah,
you know, there's a famous רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. He says, you
know, he says finding פרנסה parnassah for a Jew is צרכי מצוה.
tzorchei mitzvah. You know, things like whether you're allowed to do it
as a צורך מצוה, tzorach mitzvah, not a צורך מצוה. tzorach mitzvah.
So, you know, it has a very positive spin. You know, I'm
sure we all know right, the joke right, about the guy that
he needs to go in to talk to his business partner at
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you know, and he, you know the joke,
right? He needs to go in, but he doesn't have a, you
know, he's not Jewish or whatever, he doesn't have a ticket. So
the guard at the door won't let him in. He doesn't have
a ticket, doesn't have a seat. So he says, just please, please,
just like, an emergency, just for two seconds, please let me in.
He says, fine. You can go in. But remember, no praying. So
anyway, so that's actually a good sort of Talmudic source for the
20th century Jewish center idea. Exactly. But it actually was an actual,
this idea of the synagogue as a Jewish center is ancient. It
was like one of the primary functions. Actually a whole question, is
it called בית כנסת, Beis Knesset, right, or is it, what was
the other term used for it? There was... but you know, בית
כנסת Beis Knesset means a gathering place. You know, anyway. Okay. So
anyway, it says that separate seating means by profession. Right. Exactly. אמר
אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, let's just finish this up. וכולהו
קטלינו אלכסנדרוס מוקדון. Vekulhu katlinu Alexandros Mokdon.
And they were all wiped out by now. אלכסנדרוס מוקדון Alexandros Mokdon
is Alexander of Macedonia, which who did not wipe out the Jews
at all by 300 years. So others, so if you take a
look, there's side notes, where they cross out the word מוקדון Mokdon
then they say that it's an Alexander who was a, who was
one of, one of the Caesars. Or a, or a Roman, or,
you know, basically they attribute it to one of, either a Roman
general or a Roman Caesar. But clearly it was not. Steinzalts says
it was probably Trajan. Trajan. Right. There was another...
the הגר''א Gra's גירסא girsa is Trajan. Okay. Severus. Severus. Oh, that's
interesting. Okay. מאי טעמא איענשו? Mai ta'ama i'enshu? Now, why were they
punished of such an amazing Jewish community? So now it's quite fascinating
because we know that these community in Alexandria was pretty hellenized and
was not very פרום frum and observant and so on. Now you
could easily, if you're looking for reason of why they were wiped
out, talks about their degree of assimilation etc. But it's quite fascinating
what the גמרא Gemara is gonna answer. Why were they punished? משום
דעברו אהאי קרא, Mishum de'avru ahai kra, they transgressed the verse that
says: לא תוסיפון לשוב בדרך הזה עוד, Lo tosifun lashuv baderech hazeh
od,
because they went back to Egypt. ואינהו הדור, Ve-innu hadur, or they
went back, as they... כי אתא אשכחינהו, ki ata ashkechinhu, now when
this whoever it was Trajan came let's say, אשכחינהו דהוי קרא בספרא,
ashkechinhu d'havi kara be'sifra, he saw that they were reading in a
book, in the book of... in a ספר, sefer, ישא ה' עליך
גוי מרחוק, yisa Hashem alecha goy merachok, he found a kid let's
say, there are often stories like you find a kid reading a
פסוק pasuk and that's like an omen. Was reading the verse, "God
will bring upon you a nation from far away". אמר, Amar, so
he said to himself, look, מכדי, michtei, ההוא גברא, hahu gavra, this
person meaning me, בעי למיתי ספינתא בעשרה יומי, ba'ei l'meiti sefinta b'asara
yomei, I should have... my ship should have taken ten days to
get here, ודליה זיקא ואתי ספינתא בחמשה יומי, v'dalyei zika v'ati sefinta
b'chamsha yomei, wind blew and it came in five days. So it
must be that God was bringing me here. ישא ה' עליך גוי
מרחוק, yisa Hashem alecha goy merachok, and the end of the verse
is that He's gonna take you into captivity. So, נפל עלייהו וקטלינהו,
nafal alaive ve-katleinu, he saw it as a סימן מן השמים siman
min hashamayim and he wiped them out. So that's a lovely way
to end that story. Anyway, we'll pick up here tomorrow. Didn't hear
me?